const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",i="civiledu",o=200,t=120,a=[{id:57,question:"The first executive president of Nigeria is/was",option:{a:"Abubakar Tafawa Balewa",b:"Goodluck Jonathan",c:"NnamdiAzikiwe.",d:"Shehu Shagari."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:400,question:"Red-tapism is one the shortcomings of",option:{a:"private enterprise",b:"public service",c:"non-governmental organization",d:"pressure groups"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:429,question:"Democracy is yet to take firm root in Africa because",option:{a:"it retards African development",b:"African leaders are not experienced enough",c:"most African leaders detest the will of the people",d:"it is an expensive system of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:310,question:"If six political parties contest for an election (A, B, C, D, E, F), what is the probability that party C will wine the election",option:{a:"1/3",b:"1/4",c:"1/6",d:"1/2"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:172,question:"A constitution that is very easy to amend is called a ...... constitution",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"an easy",d:"simple"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:431,question:"Justice demands that people should always do what is",option:{a:"persistently convenient",b:"consistently right",c:"individually acceptable",d:"courageously necessary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:159,question:"Citizenship is acquired by an alien through",option:{a:"registration",b:"birth",c:"Conferment",d:"Naturalization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:61,question:"In democracy, lack of press freedom leads to the denial of freedom of",option:{a:"association",b:"expression",c:"movement",d:"voting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:185,question:"An agreed set of rules prescribing the governance of a country can be called the",option:{a:"constitution",b:"charter",c:"manifesto",d:"programme"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:294,question:"Public service belongs to ................",option:{a:"the legislative arm of government",b:"the judiciary arm of government",c:"senate arm of government",d:"the executive arm of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:43,question:"A major benefit of youth empowerment is",option:{a:"dependence on foreign aid.",b:"discouragement of patriotism",c:"reduction in crime rate",d:"negation to national prosperity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:322,question:"General Murtala Mohammed was assassinated on his way to work in ..............",option:{a:"February 13, 1976",b:"June 12, 1993",c:"October 1, 1960",d:"June 8, 1998"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:18,question:"The principle that public servants cannot be held responsible for their official actions denotes",option:{a:"impartiality",b:"accountability",c:"anonymity",d:"neutrality."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:155,question:"When Ebola disease is very rampant ............. count 	their loses while ......... smile to the bank",option:{a:"fish sellers, bush meat sellers",b:"bush meat sellers, fish sellers",c:"bread sellers, fish sellers",d:"students, teachers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:342,question:"The former PHCN is a good example of .................. in Nigeria",option:{a:"civil service",b:"perfect competition",c:"public corporation",d:"private monopoly"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:95,question:"One of the ways to ensure a free and fair election is to",option:{a:"allow parties to campaign on election day",b:"appoint a politician as the chairman of the electoral commission",c:"ensure INEC chairman is appointed from a pressure group",d:"guarantee the security of electoral officers and materials"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:364,question:"Cult members are particularly hostile to",option:{a:"lecturers",b:"perceived enemies",c:"their group members",d:"all students"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:101,question:"............ is obtained from the Nigerian immigration services as a requirement to travel out of the country",option:{a:"ticket",b:"yellow card",c:"passport",d:"national ID card"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:140,question:"One of the following is a regulatory prohibitory sign",option:{a:"stop police",b:"speed limit",c:"t junction",d:"ferry"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:392,question:"Two forms of road signs are regulatory and",option:{a:"punitive",b:"informative",c:"persuasive",d:"inhibitive"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:270,question:"During a particular voting exercise if majority of the 	people refuse to vote, this can be described as",option:{a:"political stubbornness",b:"political apathy",c:"political awareness",d:"political socialization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:411,question:"Which of the following statements best describes Human Trafficking?",option:{a:"Recruitment of youths as casual workers",b:"Desperate desire by youths to travel abroad",c:"Buying and selling of humans for selfish purposes",d:"Transportation of gods and service through human portage"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:175,question:"A governmental system in which constitutional supremacy resides in the centre is",option:{a:"federal",b:"confederal",c:"unitary",d:"parliamentary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:414,question:"Based on the write-up, what immediate measures can those in authority take to empower the youths?",option:{a:"Build more youth orientation camps in the country",b:"Enhance religious and moral education in schools and colleges",c:"Provide entrepreneurial training with adequate fund",d:"Provide free meal for the teeming unemployed youths"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:52,question:"The following are values that promote interpersonal relationship, except",option:{a:"caring.",b:"honesty.",c:"patience",d:"properties."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:388,question:"Citizen’s compliance with tenets of the Nigerian National Pledge will enable the country to",option:{a:"receive reciprocal assistance",b:"witness value clarification",c:"get international aid",d:"experience development"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:386,question:"Based on the above story, which of the following would Dr.Fajir not be allowed to do while in prison?",option:{a:"Voting during elections",b:"Engaging in hard labour",c:"Participating in prison fellowship",d:"Writing examination"},section:"Dr. Fajir was the Minister of Works and Urban Development in the Gambia Republic. As such, he was entrusted with the public fund so that his ministry could construct new roads and rehabilitate the existing ones. Unfortunately. Dr Fajir embezzled the money entrusted in his care and siphoned same to his foreign accounts. This led to the deplorable conditions of roads in the Republic. The Crime Commission arrested and prosecuted him accordingly. Subsequently, he was given the opportunity to be defended by lawyers of his choice in a Court of Law. However, he was found guilty and sentenced to 15 years imprisonment with hard labour without the option of a fine. In addition, he forfeited all his ill-gotten wealth to the Republic.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:266,question:"If you were to be in the Governor’s shoes which of the following would you have chosen?",option:{a:"Miranda and seven up",b:"coca cola and Fanta",c:"petroleum",d:"stock, bonds and cash"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:118,question:"The following factors are responsible for drug abuse except",option:{a:"family upbringing",b:"high stress level",c:"poverty",d:"foster parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:359,question:"The effect of human trafficking on the victims is",option:{a:"illiteracy",b:"affluence",c:"exposure",d:"exploitation"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:348,question:"Lack of interest in politics by citizens in the country is referred to as political",option:{a:"ignorance",b:"apathy",c:"participation",d:"socialization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:31,question:"One of the reasons most HIV/AIDS patients are 	reluctant to disclose their status is because of",option:{a:"the incurable nature of the ailment",b:"fear of social stigmatization.",c:"lack of sufficient public awareness",d:"shortage of health counsellors"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:236,question:"The lack of interest in politics and political activities by the citizens of a country is known as",option:{a:"political disinterestedness",b:"political culture",c:"political disintegration",d:"political apathy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:121,question:".......... strengthens the sensitive mental and emotional bond between the parent and children",option:{a:"narcissistic parenting",b:"attachment parenting",c:"positive parenting",d:"teenage parenting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:124,question:"All the following can limit the right of a citizen except",option:{a:"war",b:"state of emergency",c:"universality",d:"military rule"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:74,question:"How many Senator(s) represent the Federal Capital Territory in the senate?",option:{a:"1",b:"2",c:"3",d:"4"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:60,question:"ln 2013, Nigeria celebrated her ______ independence anniversary",option:{a:"50th",b:"51st",c:"52nd",d:"54th"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:91,question:"The headquarters of ECOWAS is located in",option:{a:"Abuja",b:"Accra",c:"Adis-Ababa",d:"Lome"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:269,question:"Human traffickers usually engage their victims .........",option:{a:"in educative programs",b:"in forced labour",c:"in skill acquisition activities",d:"in recreational activities"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:355,question:"Which of the following is not an example of orderliness?",option:{a:"Listening skill",b:"Driving skill",c:"Decorum",d:"Deviance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:264,question:"For now the Ebola disease has",option:{a:"no known cure",b:"several known cures",c:"cannot kill its action",d:"no physically observable symptoms"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:181,question:"Public Corporations are financed",option:{a:"by tax payers",b:"with private funds",c:"with entrepreneurial funds",d:"by political parties"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:112,question:"The 219 chibok girls were ................ while ..............",option:{a:"abducted, praying in the mosque",b:"kidnaped, praying in the church",c:"abducted, wondering along the street of chibok town",d:"kidnaped, preparing to write their WAEC examination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:335,question:"The killing of NYSC members in certain parts of the country  ................",option:{a:"Contradicts the goal of establishing the scheme",b:"Is in line with the aims of establishing the scheme",c:"Is not a serious matter",d:"Enhances national unity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:127,question:"One of the following is not human right group",option:{a:"Constitutional Right Project (CRP)",b:"National Association of Democratic Lawyers (NADL)",c:"Nigeria Bar Association (NBA)",d:"Civil Liberties Organization (CLO)"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:218,question:"Which one of the following is the founding father of Nigeria nationalism?",option:{a:"Goodluck Jonathan",b:"Oba Kosoko",c:"Herbert Macaulay",d:"Olusegun Obasanjo"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:290,question:"Which of these categories of people stand the greatest risk of contacting the Ebola virus .........",option:{a:"Lecturers and students in the school",b:"Health workers and their family members",c:"Hunters and their family members",d:"b and c above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:393,question:"Which of the following factors does not affect interpersonal relationship?",option:{a:"Communication",b:"Withdrawal",c:"Compatibility",d:"Forgiveness"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:283,question:"Consumers of ......... especially ........... and ..............stand the a great risk of contacting the Ebola disease",option:{a:"fish, tilapia, titus",b:"bush meat, monkey, bat",c:"meat, cow, dog",d:"vegetable, water leaf, bitter leaf"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:321,question:"NUC and NBA stands for ......... and ......... respectively",option:{a:"National University Commission and Nigeria Bar Association",b:"Nigeria Bar Association and National University Commission",c:"National Union Congress and Nigeria Basketball Authority",d:"National Utilities Commission and Nigeria Bar Association"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:233,question:"The principle of equality before the law is the same as",option:{a:"social equality",b:"social injustices",c:"checks and balances",d:"democratic justices"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:150,question:"The colour of the Nigeria flag is ..............., anytime it 	is half masked it means that the nation is ...............",option:{a:"green white green - rejoicing",b:"white green white - mourning",c:"green white green - mourning",d:"green white blue - voting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:219,question:"The use of illicit or hard drugs such as marijuana (Indian hemp) heroine, morphine etc. is known as",option:{a:"Human right abuse",b:"Drug trafficking",c:"Drug enhancement",d:"Drug abuse"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:129,question:"One of the following is not a political party",option:{a:"PDP",b:"APGA",c:"ANPC",d:"CPC"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:105,question:"Newspapers and magazine and example of ..... media",option:{a:"print",b:"electronic",c:"advertising",d:"mass"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:419,question:"The above quotation summarizes the",option:{a:"Universal Declaration of Human Rights.",b:"African Charter on Human Rights.",c:"Geneva Conventions and Protocols.",d:"United Nations Organization Charter."},section:"“All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and 		conscience and should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood”.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:40,question:"Which of the following governmental agencies is the most capable of controlling the activities of Wanja and his group?",option:{a:"National Agency for Food and Drug Administration and Control (NAFDAC)",b:"National Orientation Agency (NO A)",c:"National Emergency Management Agency (NEMA)",d:"National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA)"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:410,question:"The NDLEA personnel are not usually found in",option:{a:"international airports",b:"seaports",c:"border crossings",d:"foreign embassies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:133,question:"............... is the prejudicial treatment of fellow human being",option:{a:"god fatherism",b:"independence",c:"justice",d:"discrimination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:137,question:"When a group of people believe in and keep to certain norms, values and ways of life of their community since its creation, we call this .................",option:{a:"religion",b:"stereotypes",c:"traditions",d:"custom"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:343,question:"Orderliness can be defined as",option:{a:"being punctual to work",b:"studying diligently in school",c:"doing things in a proper way",d:"learning the Western way of life"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:300,question:"Which of the following are Ebola Emergency lines",option:{a:"08023169484 or 08033086660",b:"08023361936 or 08034623521",c:"08023164216 or 08033065936",d:"08055281400 or 08023361936"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:36,question:"From this dialogue, it is very likely that Wanja will be exhibiting the following characters except",option:{a:"disobedience to constituted authority",b:"truancy and perpetual lateness to school",c:"hospitable attitude towards people",d:"arrogance and unruly behaviour."},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:281,question:"Juvenile delinquency refers to",option:{a:"active youths participation in sports",b:"wrong doings by the youths",c:"Refusal to worship God by the youths",d:"Urban Rural migration by the youth"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:111,question:"The last population census in Nigeria was conducted in ...........",option:{a:"2003",b:"2006",c:"2007",d:"2005"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:333,question:"At the end of the service year each corper will be given ......... as an evidence that he or she has successfully completed the service",option:{a:"NYSC passport",b:"National ID Card",c:"NYSC discharge certificate",d:"Letter of appreciation"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:39,question:"From the above dialogue, Wanja’s behaviour could be curtailed by",option:{a:"sending him abroad for further studies",b:"financial inducement",c:"re - orientation and rehabilitation",d:"indulging him with expensive gifts"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:320,question:"The former National anthem begins with.......................",option:{a:"Nigeria We Hail Thee",b:"Arise O Compatriots",c:"I pledge to Nigeria my Country",d:"So help me God"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:146,question:"Political values are acquired in any given society through",option:{a:"Political re-orientation",b:"Political campaign",c:"Political socialization",d:"Political indoctrination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:67,question:"The right of an individual to seek redress in a law court is categorized under",option:{a:"economic.",b:"political",c:"procedural,",d:"social"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:358,question:"Which of the following is a consequence of drug abuse?",option:{a:"Depression",b:"Victimization",c:"Inefficiency",d:"Cowardice"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:368,question:"The Supreme Court of Nigeria helps in law",option:{a:"drafting",b:"application",c:"interpretation",d:"enforcement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:119,question:"........ is the type of parenthood where a different couple raise a particular child that is not their own",option:{a:"helicopter parent",b:"foster parenthood",c:"slow parenting",d:"different parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:25,question:"Democratic governance is usually characterized by",option:{a:"free, fair and credible elections",b:"buoyant and competitive economy",c:"accessible employment opportunities",d:"youth participation in governance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:261,question:"On a particular day in 2014, the National flag was flown half mask. This act symbolizes",option:{a:"National tailors day",b:"National mourning",c:"Children’s day",d:"Golden jubilee celebration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:243,question:"An organization whose ultimate aim is to gain the control of government and implement its programmes is known as a",option:{a:"Trade Union",b:"Local Government",c:"Political Party",d:"Pressure Group"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:263,question:"In which of the following system is survival of the fittest mostly practiced",option:{a:"Communist system",b:"Capitalist system",c:"Feudalist",d:"Totalistic system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:41,question:"One of the major barriers to national development is the",option:{a:"low poverty level",b:"existence of multi - party system",c:"prevalence of corrupt practices",d:"persistent rural - urban migration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:122,question:"........... is the verdict that results when a law court declares a defendant guilty of a crime",option:{a:"immunity clause",b:"conviction",c:"customary clause",d:"traditions"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:125,question:"The following are causes of emergency rule except",option:{a:"crisis",b:"blood lettings",c:"stage peaceful protest",d:"sabotage / terrorism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:173,question:"In a democratic government, political sovereignty is vested in the",option:{a:"legislature",b:"elite",c:"executive",d:"electorate"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:148,question:"The right of citizens to participate in the affairs of government of their country is called",option:{a:"economic right",b:"civil right",c:"political right",d:"social right"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:254,question:"The Ebola virus sneaked into Nigeria through",option:{a:"The Liberian born American, Mr Patrick Sawyer",b:"The Ghanaian born American, Mr Patrick Sayer",c:"Members of the Boko Haram",d:"Monkeys and bats"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:406,question:"Which of the following is not included in the stages of interpersonal relationship?",option:{a:"Rejuvenation",b:"Deterioration",c:"Termination",d:"Continuation"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:423,question:"The idea that “Law should be impartial with the people who break it” implies",option:{a:"principle of fair hearing",b:"right to legal representation",c:"equality before the law",d:"prerogative writ of habeas corpus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:183,question:"Which of the following is not a duty of a citizen",option:{a:"obedience to the law",b:"payment of taxes",c:"service to the Nation",d:"giving alms to the poor"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:160,question:"The office responsible for announcing the result of an election is known as",option:{a:"ballot officer",b:"presiding officer",c:"Returning officer",d:"Electoral officer"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:307,question:"Civic Education is also known as ....................",option:{a:"Organizational Structure",b:"Citizenship Education",c:"Customers Opinion",d:"Government Policy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:12,question:"Youth empowerment is best described as the",option:{a:"training given to individuals for acquiring means livelihood",b:"practice of engaging in prospective career",c:"provision of subsidized meals to the citizens by government,",d:"mobilization of citizens for political rally."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:13,question:"The National Assembly, Presidency and Court which are inter - related and interdependent in our democracy constitute the",option:{a:"tiers of government",b:"types of democracy",c:"forms of government.",d:"arms of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:54,question:"Most African countries owed their creation to",option:{a:"African Union (AU).",b:"Commonwealth of Nations.",c:"Ethnic and tribal leaders.",d:"European Colonialists"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:409,question:"An individual who finds it difficult to control in-take of drug is known as drug",option:{a:"baron",b:"traffickers",c:"mogul",d:"addict"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:398,question:"An enabling environment created to help an individual have effective control of his/her situation is known as",option:{a:"reinforcement",b:"empowerment",c:"endowment",d:"enhancement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:417,question:"Inter-communal relationship is best described as",option:{a:"the interaction between individuals, groups or organizations with common aspirations",b:"the interaction among individuals and professionals in a social setting",c:"loyalty to community leaders so as to achieve rapid communal development",d:"respect for collective national symbols in order to foster nationalistic feeling"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:255,question:"As a citizen you can be deprived of your Fundamental Human Rights during",option:{a:"Emergency Rule",b:"Election period",c:"National day celebration",d:"National public holidays"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:80,question:"A de-facto authority is mostly associated with",option:{a:"anarchy.",b:"customs and tradition.",c:"force.",d:"law."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:103,question:"Local government is the ............... tier of government",option:{a:"1st",b:"2nd",c:"3rd",d:"4th"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:337,question:"Some years to come, when you become the President of Nigeria, which of the options below will you choose 	to eradicate porzverty in the country",option:{a:"carry all the poor people away from Nigeria to another country so when there are no poor people poverty will be gone forever",b:"print plenty Naira Notes and give millions to every Nigeria",c:"Import plenty Agricultural and Manufactured goods",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:38,question:"From Ada’s admonition, it could be deduced that taking hard drugs could",option:{a:"make people respect the addicts.",b:"lead to insanity of the addicts",c:"make people to adore the drug addicts",d:"ensure courteous behaviour by the addicts"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:63,question:"How many members constitute the lower legislative chamber in Nigeria?",option:{a:"300",b:"302",c:"312",d:"360"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:331,question:"Those eligible to partake in the scheme are those",option:{a:"Those seeking for admission into the higher institutions",b:"Who have successfully completed their studies from higher institution .eg. college of education, 		     polytechnic & university",c:"Who are looking for something to keep them busy",d:"Who are from poor family background"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:247,question:"Those who consume fish and vegetable frequently stand the chance of contacting the",option:{a:"HIV/AIDs disease",b:"Ebola disease",c:"Typhoid and yellow fever disease",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:273,question:"The attitude of the crowd towards, the sick man was that of ............",option:{a:"indifference",b:"friendliness",c:"hospitality",d:"political apathy"},section:"A certain man came to visit his friend at Shomolu one early morning. Unexpectedly the man fainted and slumped. He lay on the floor for several hours and looking lifeless. The crowd and even the friend he came to visit kept a reasonable distance from him. No one came to his rescue or even attempted to touch him. As luck would have it he regained his strength after about five hours and managed to go back to his house",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:387,question:"The most important place for building good values is the",option:{a:"social welfare centre",b:"workplace",c:"family",d:"media houses"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:253,question:"As Mr Umukoro got to Oghara junction, near Sapele, he packed the bus and bought some roasted monkey bush meat. Some of the passengers in the bus followed suit, that day was a good Friday. On motion Mr Umukoro, the driver and some of the passengers were doing justice to the monkey bush meat. No sooner had they started than they were stopped and Mr Umukoro was fined by men of the FRSC. If the fine was proper which of the reasons bellow could be responsible for it",option:{a:"some of the passengers ate the bush meat while the bus was on motion",b:"Mr Umukoro, the driver was driving and eating at the same time",c:"They were not supposed to eat monkey bush meat because they can contact the Ebola virus from it.",d:"They were not expected to eat and any kind of meat on a good Friday"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:177,question:"A government is said to be legitimate if it",option:{a:"has the people’s mandate to rule",b:"is not oppressive",c:"provide social services for the people",d:"accepts people’s criticism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:318,question:"Which of the following was a former military head of state in Nigeria",option:{a:"MKO Abiola",b:"Goodluck Jonathan",c:"General Idiagbon",d:"General Babagida"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:228,question:"It is an offense to drive along the high way",option:{a:"without putting on the seat belt",b:"and talk or smile at the same time",c:"and make phone calls at the same time",d:"A and C above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:277,question:"Any forms of restricted franchise is a violation of the principle of",option:{a:"political equality",b:"sovereignty",c:"legality",d:"constitutionalism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:433,question:"Which of the following is necessary for the effective application of the rule of law?",option:{a:"Political will to ensure that laws are obeyed",b:"Employment opportunities for all citizens",c:"The fusion of the three arms of government",d:"Extension of the retirement age of judges"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:227,question:"The system of government in which all aspects of life are controlled by the government is",option:{a:"democracy",b:"totalitarianism",c:"capitalism",d:"socialism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:257,question:"Plenty of money in the society, not backed by commensurate productive activities can lead to",option:{a:"deflation",b:"inflation",c:"National developmental",d:"cashless society"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:5,question:"Human Rights are basic natural rights which people enjoy primarily because they are",option:{a:"members of a political party",b:"international citizens",c:"members of a community",d:"human beings."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:192,question:"Colonization of Africa was mainly motivated by",option:{a:"security consideration",b:"economic reasons",c:"religious reasons",d:"cultural factor"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:250,question:"When a constitution is difficult to amend it is said to be",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"written",d:"federal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:102,question:"There are ............. local government in Nigeria",option:{a:"700",b:"714",c:"744",d:"774"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:154,question:"The major factor militating against efficient operation 	of electoral commission in Nigeria is .......................",option:{a:"Inadequate public support",b:"Population size",c:"Inadequate skilled manpower",d:"excessive political interference"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:188,question:"The following are examples of pressure group except",option:{a:"N. U. R. T",b:"NBA",c:"NLC",d:"PDP"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:308,question:"The number of Girls abducted by members of Boko Haram at Chibok in 2014 is roughly",option:{a:"200",b:"219",c:"419",d:"180"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:162,question:"The ultimate aim of political parties is to",option:{a:"implement people oriented programmes",b:"acquire and exercise power",c:"increase the political awareness of the electorate",d:"formulate and implement policies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"}],n={message:e,subject:i,status:200,total:120,data:a};export{a as data,n as default,e as message,o as status,i as subject,t as total};
